In science news, that makes you want to
stare at a wall for a few hours, brain
organoids, yes, the tiny human brains
you can grow from stem cells, grow
better in the presence of a human
heartbeat.
Yes, brain organoids, the tiny adorable
miniature versions of the human brain,
and it's important to note that they
don't normally have any kind of sensory
input, and when you give them sensory
input, yes, those are eyes, and they can
occasionally grow eyes under the right
conditions, they do sense light under
those circumstances because eyeballs are
part of your nervous system. Now, if you
want to give them sensory input, you
would have to attach another organoid to
them, like a spinal organoid, or in the
case of when they're used for
computation, they give them electric
shocks, and those are symbolic of
something that they would encounter in
the virtual world. But researchers
hypothesized that the presence of a
heartbeat would improve their
development, and it seems to be the
case. Now, some important notes, this is
a preprint, but it is coming out of a
well-respected lab in Germany. One of
the issues with brain organoids is that
they still remain fairly small, just a
few millimeters across, and if you want
to have a good model that's comparable
to a human being for research, you're
going to have to have a very complex
brain organoid, or at least as close to
human complexity as you can get.
Organoids can be a stand-in for human
beings when it comes to research, and
yes, they can also be used for
computation. In either case, you want it
to be as close to an adult brain as
possible. Astrocytes are human cells
that are involved in the structural
stability, development, and maintenance
of the human nervous system.
Enriching brain organoids with
astrocytes could make them more
structurally sound and develop more
completely, and that seems to be the
case, but it is really the case when
they listen to a heartbeat.
Astrocytes alone did lead to more
structural complexity and more activity
on behalf of the brain organoids, but
with astrocytes and a heartbeat, they
really did.
And you can see the difference between
the control and the heartbeat model in
terms of how active they were. And these
were not organoids that were trained to
do anything. This is just the random
firing of their neurons all on their
own.
Again, they have no way to perceive the
heartbeat. This is just their
development in the presence of it.
Now, this does not indicate
consciousness or intelligence. It does
indicate that a heartbeat may be
important to our fetal development. It
would be interesting to see brain
organoids compared from an animal that
hatches in an egg, like say a bird to a
mouse and see if heartbeat is necessary.
Now, one of the things that does bother
me about this is that if we end up using
biological neural networks, so brain
organoids in servers, will we have to
raise them with a heartbeat in order to
make them the most efficient? And to be
honest, if I have to sing a lullaby to
the server rack, I am out.
Now, if you know me and my content, I
have been covering brain organoids for
the last few years, and there have been
some absolutely amazing advancements.
And apparently, they will also survive
transport if you mail them.
That is actually really good news for
researchers. We have seen an absolute
explosion in this field.
At least in mice and Simeon models, and
that includes chimpanzees. They could be
used to heal strokes. They could be an
actual treatment in which they are
transplanted into an injured region, and
multiple research groups have found them
effective for spinal injuries. So, these
guys are extraordinarily exciting.
So, the idea of trying to make them as
complex and as human as possible so they
can serve as good research subjects, but
also as good treatments, it's not
entirely spooky, even though it is kind
of creepy. I will admit though, the
whole heartbeat thing really did get me
this time.
I don't just feign incredulousness for
the camera. A lot of these papers
actually do shock me. They are
extraordinarily cool though, but
sometimes they make me want to stare at
the ceiling.
Give me time. I may be prepared to sing
lullabies to the server rack.
I do hope you've enjoyed this. I will
keep you up to date. You have no choice.
Follow for more.